<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Practical Systems Engineering</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://johntrinh.net/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://johntrinh.net/</id><updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering of the Mind</subtitle><entry><title>Task Conflict in Engineering</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/task-conflict-in-engineering.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:johntrinh.net,2021-02-07:/task-conflict-in-engineering.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Why engineers are good at solving problems, and the archetype that technical development teams shouldn't tolerate.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physicist Richard Feynman once said, "The first principle is that you must not fool yourself, and you are the easiest person to fool." One way we fool ourselves is by imagining we know more than we do; we think we are experts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past week's episode of the &lt;a href="https://hiddenbrain.org/podcast/the-easiest-person-to-fool/"&gt;Hidden Brain&lt;/a&gt; podcast got me thinking about how engineers deal with this in their everyday work, and how the best teams &amp;amp; companies develop a culture that encourages task conflict without relationship conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we think about conflict, we usually think about a disagreement between people where someone takes things personally, as an attack on their character or their beliefs. In the podcast, author Adam Grant describes this as &lt;strong&gt;Relationship Conflict.&lt;/strong&gt; By contrast, &lt;strong&gt;Task Conflict&lt;/strong&gt; is "the idea of debating about different opinions and perspectives; it's potentially constructive because it's actually about trying to get to the truth. It's not personal, it's not emotional, we're not trying to beat up the other person... we're trying to hash out or sort out different views."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made me realize that task conflict is something engineers are trained to do intuitively. When we need to develop a solution to a problem, we debate on the physics, math, design approach, costs, and risks of the solution. The goal is always to move the ball towards a technical solution. While it's impossible to completely avoid relationship conflicts, any engineer who's ever contributed meaningfully to an engineering project probably valued creating the most optimal solutions over validating their worth or ego.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Keys to Task Conflict in Engineering&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are engineers able to do this? What is it about our profession that cultivates task conflict while actively rejecting relationship conflict? From my experience, I think there are several keys to our success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Engineering Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll go into detail in a future article, but the process of engineering is inherently problem focused. The process every engineering student is taught in school as part of their fundamentals is reinforced as they become working professionals. The process leaves little room for relationship conflict because such conflict is an inefficient way of problem-solving that distracts from the purpose of the team and the program as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Engineering Leadership&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The twenty-fourth Unwritten Law of Sytems Engineering states: "You need a management style with a firm manner and that gives the appearance that you know which way to lead. Hang tough."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burnout can happen from working unsustainably long hours, but it can also happen when individuals feel like they're fighting against the system rather than being supported by it in order to do their jobs. Engineers show up to problem solve, and when they have to fight uphill in order to execute technical work, that's when burnout happens. In some extreme cases, there is so much friction between company leadership and the technical work that entire teams of engineers will simply leave the company, causing a faiure cascade as junior engineers are left without the guidance formerly provided by their seniors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the best managers I've worked with understand that engineering needs to be supported by company leadership in order to thrive. To make their technical programs successful, they created a healthy rivalry with management instead of fighting against it, and shielded their teams from "management BS" when necessary (which was often). These managers effectively isolated any relationship conflict between themselves and management, allowing their team to stay focused on technical work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Believing in 'The Mission'&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also call this phenomenon "the thrill of the problem." In Tracy Kidder's famous non-fiction &lt;em&gt;The Soul of a New Machine&lt;/em&gt;, he tells the story of Data General Corporation and the technical development team behind a new minicomputer in the 1980s. One of the focal themes of this story is that many engineers will work their asses off when given a challenging &amp;amp; fulfilling problem to work on — especially under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The people working on &lt;em&gt;EGO&lt;/em&gt; [...] truly labored. They worked nights. They worked weekends. They argued hotly with each other. "It was the most incredible, soaring experience of my life," said one of them later. And they worked with astonishing speed. Within two months they had a fairly complete specification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cult of SpaceX isn't a new thing — it's simply a modern, scaled-up and highly public manifestation of engineering culture that has existed for as long as engineering itself has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Rejecting the "Brilliant Asshole" Archetype&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Julie Zhuo's excellent field guide to management, &lt;em&gt;The Making of a Manager&lt;/em&gt;, she describes the one thing you shouldn't tolerate on your team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a certain archetype of the brilliant lone wolf, who, though he regularly puts others down, manages to come out the hero because he is simply heads and tails more capable than anyone else. It's a romantic notion in popular media — Sherlock Holmes, Miranda Priestly, Tony Stark — but in real life, these people are not who you want on your team no matter how talented they are. Instead of a multiplier effect, you get a divider effect: the presence of this person makes the rest of your team less effective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't think this last point is an axiom like the others. Many engineering teams put up with someone like this on their program, either because of the circumstances — the program doesn't have enough budget to find a replacement — or because the company leadership or technical managers are too inexperienced to recognize the divisive effect this type of person has on the rest of the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Concluding Thoughts&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distinction between task conflict and relationship conflict is an interesting one. We're so used to relationship conflict in popular media and our own lives that we often expect it by default. But engineering culture shows that it's possible to separate the two in order to achieve something greater than any one person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The appeal of this to me is that anyone can apply this to their own lives. There's nothing wrong with some healthy conflict between people which helps everyone grow, and to form stronger, more genuine relationships. The problem is often conflict without compassion, which results in toxicity that drives people apart rather than everyone feeling like they're being heard &amp;amp; understood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to explore this topic again in deeper detail to look at what makes healthy, authentic relationships, and how engineerieng problem-solving skills fit into this picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Podcast: https://hiddenbrain.org/podcast/the-easiest-person-to-fool&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unwritten Laws of Systems Engineering: https://github.com/specifics/aero-structures/blob/master/SysEngLaw.md&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Burnout: https://www.twitch.tv/videos/916814991?t=50m&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The Making of a Manager" by Julie Zhuo, Portfolio/Penguin (2019): p.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Engineering"></category><category term="engineering"></category><category term="psychology"></category></entry><entry><title>5 Apps to Improve Your Security &amp; Privacy in 2019 (Updated for 2020)</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/5-apps-to-improve-your-security-and-privacy-in-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:johntrinh.net,2019-06-23:/5-apps-to-improve-your-security-and-privacy-in-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short list of apps to streamline your personal online security &amp;amp; privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t receive any compensation, monetary or otherwise, from the products, companies, or developers of the apps discussed in this article.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; There are many privacy-focused apps listed on &lt;a href="https://prism-break.org/en/"&gt;PRISM Break.&lt;/a&gt; If there's an app or function you're looking for outside the scope of this article, chances are there's something listed there you can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As online technologies continue to grow, data collection and surveillance on users has become the norm. The entities who do this are not only &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/nsa-spying"&gt;government agencies,&lt;/a&gt; but also &lt;a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/08/when-it-comes-to-internet-privacy-be-very-afraid-analyst-suggests/"&gt;corporations&lt;/a&gt; and the very companies that develop the tools we all use. It’s no surprise given how lucrative data collection has become as a business model for internet companies like Google and Facebook to &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/2018/4/11/17177842/facebook-advertising-ads-explained-mark-zuckerberg"&gt;sell ads and share personal data with third-parties.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s disheartening for me to see the weekly headlines of millions of users’ worth of data being hacked, or that the companies we’ve entrusted our information with have decided to do questionable or unethical things with our data for profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nulltext" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/kill-code.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even worse, our &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2018/4/10/17222062/mark-zuckerberg-testimony-graham-facebook-regulations"&gt;government seems incapable of dealing with these issues,&lt;/a&gt; either because they lack the technical expertise, or perhaps because it simply isn’t a priority issue in our current political climate. It’s hard not to feel powerless, and yet all of us rely on these tools as a part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opting out doesn’t work. It’s nonsense to tell people not to carry a credit card or not to have an email address. And “buyer beware” is putting too much onus on the individual. People don’t test their food for pathogens or their airlines for safety. The government does it. But the government has failed in protecting consumers from internet companies and social media giants. But this will come around. The only effective way to control big corporations is through big government. —&lt;a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/08/when-it-comes-to-internet-privacy-be-very-afraid-analyst-suggests/"&gt;Bruce Schneier, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, I decided to do something to protect my online privacy so that I’d have some protection when the real-world situation gets worse. My hope is that you’ll be convinced it’s not as difficult and time-consuming to do as you might imagine, and get motivated to protect yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These apps aren’t a magic bullet; they’re simply tools. The real benefits come from changing some of your bad online habits and adopting better ones. Even if you don’t adopt every aspect today, acknowledging that your online privacy isn’t good enough and committing to improve over time is a great first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1. Iridium Browser, Brave, and Firefox&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Iridium" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/iridium-browser.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Chrome has taken over the internet. As of 2019, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_web_browsers"&gt;it’s used by more than 60% of all devices!&lt;/a&gt; And for good reasons: it’s one of the more secure, actively developed browsers for desktop and mobile devices, and it’s packed with convenient features. But in recent years, it’s been &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2019/06/21/google-chrome-has-become-surveillance-software-its-time-switch/"&gt;under scrutiny&lt;/a&gt; for adding questionable features that invade user privacy, and &lt;a href="https://blog.cryptographyengineering.com/2018/09/23/why-im-leaving-chrome/"&gt;keep them handcuffed to the Google ecosystem.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a challenge to find a desktop web browser that’s based on the open-source Chromium code like Google Chrome is, but without all of the baggage. I finally found an alternative in &lt;a href="http://iridiumbrowser.de/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iridium Browser,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is an open-source project that focuses on security and privacy. If you don’t have a strong preference for the Chromium look &amp;amp; feel, &lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firefox&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://brave.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brave&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are other great options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of which browser you decide to use, don’t forget to add the following extensions for maximum protection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uBlock Origin + uBlock Origin Extra &lt;em&gt;(Note: Adblock Plus is no longer trustworthy)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. Brave for mobile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Brave" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/brave-browser.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for mobile browsers, I’m a big fan of &lt;a href="https://brave.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brave&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is available for iOS and Android. It comes with the best mobile ad-blocker I’ve ever used (it can even block YouTube ads and allow video playback in the background while your phone is locked). The experience feels extremely optimized and lightweight compared to any other mobile browser I’ve used in the past 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While they are a for-profit company, &lt;a href="https://www.computerworld.com/article/3292619/the-brave-browser-basics-what-it-does-how-it-differs-from-rivals.html"&gt;they’re trying to improve the way ads are used&lt;/a&gt; by only allowing ads with your consent, ads that don’t collect your data, and giving users more control over what types of ads they see. Oftentimes ads are the only way some of our favorite websites can continue to operate, so this respectful user-focused approach is refreshing to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;3. 1Password or Bitwarden&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1Password" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/1password-preview.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passwords are a necessary evil for most services connected to the internet. The best way to create a truly secure (hard to crack) password is by making it longer, on the order of 32+ characters — but this is at odds with human nature since we want to use passwords that are easy to remember and type out. In other words, we’re lazy and our passwords suck. &lt;a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/"&gt;It’s possible that some of your passwords have already been leaked.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also met many people who store their passwords in a Word/text file on their computer, or wrote them all down on a legal pad. Not only is this insecure, but if you ever lost it in a hard drive failure, fire, theft, or hack, it’s game over — you’d never fully recover. Simplistic systems like this aren’t going to cut it if you want to protect yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Password managers are the solution. The idea is to create one &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/essays/archives/2014/02/choosing_a_secure_pa.html"&gt;secure and memorable passphrase&lt;/a&gt; that you commit to memory forever, and use that to login to a service or app that manages the rest of your passwords for you. The manager should also help you generate secure/randomized passwords since you no longer have to remember them for each individual account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, my most recommended services are &lt;a href="https://1password.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1Password&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, followed by &lt;a href="https://bitwarden.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bitwarden.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I researched these based on security, ease of use, and integration with browser &amp;amp; mobile. I also encourage you to check out &lt;a href="https://www.lastpass.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LastPass&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.dashlane.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dashlane&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to see which one you like best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before using any password manager, make sure you trust that your desktop and phone aren’t compromised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4. Authy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Authy" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/authy-preview.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-factor authentication (2FA), also known as One-Time Passwords (OTP), is an effective way to secure an account by separating the login credentials into two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something you know,&lt;/strong&gt; i.e. your username &amp;amp; passphrase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something you have,&lt;/strong&gt; i.e. your phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you log in to an account with 2FA enabled, the website will ask you for an additional code that’s randomly generated and sent to your phone. All codes automatically expire every minute, ensuring that no one except you can use it. Some implementations of 2FA use e-mail and SMS text messages, but these aren’t fully secure because both message forms can be easily intercepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where &lt;a href="https://authy.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; comes in. If you decide to start using a password manager, the only things you should ever have to type in again are your master passphrase so you can manage your online accounts, and your 2FA codes. This solution works really well when you do them together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might take you a day or two to set up, but isn’t as cumbersome as it first sounds. It’s well worth the increased security and peace of mind. If you do only one thing from this entire article, this is it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;5. Tutanota&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tutanota" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/tutanota-preview.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the hardest things I had to get rid of were my dozen or so e-mail addresses scattered across different services. I had several Gmail addresses, two with Outlook/Microsoft, Yahoo, and numerous others that I hardly ever used. Like many, I used Gmail as my primary e-mail service, and was fairly happy using it with their &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/mail/answer/15049?hl=en"&gt;HTML-only option.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t make the mistake of thinking you’re Facebook’s customer, you’re not — you’re the product. Its customers are the advertisers. —&lt;a href="https://www.information-age.com/facebook-is-deliberately-killing-privacy-says-schneier-1290603/"&gt;Bruce Schneier, 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was prompted to switch away from Gmail last year when the &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt; revealed that &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/7/2/17527972/gmail-app-developers-full-email-access"&gt;Google had been allowing third-party apps read data from your e-mails.&lt;/a&gt; Also don’t forget that &lt;a href="http://news.trust.org/item/20161004170601-99f8c"&gt;Yahoo was caught scanning e-mails for the NSA&lt;/a&gt; in 2016. I was upset, and disappointed in myself for not switching sooner. So began my search for an e-mail provider that wouldn’t violate my privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a lot of research, I decided on &lt;a href="https://www.tutanota.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutanota,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is available via web, iOS, and Android, and also has a dedicated desktop client for all platforms. Tutanota also comes with an encrypted calendar, which went live on July 8th, and has more features planned for development. While not as robust as Google Calendar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a privacy-focused company, their code is open-source with development to allow outside auditing. They’re a company based in Germany, which means they’re GDPR-compliant and subject to Germany’s &lt;a href="https://www.dotmagazine.online/issues/security/germany-land-of-data-protection-and-security-but-why"&gt;strong privacy laws for individuals.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you can use the limited Basic service for free, I pay $10/year for their Premium level, which gives me five different e-mail aliases, which are simply different addresses that all deliver e-mail to me. I selectively changed all of my online accounts to use a different alias depending on what the account is for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;em&gt;Address A&lt;/em&gt; for banking/finance; &lt;em&gt;Address B&lt;/em&gt; for social media; &lt;em&gt;Address C&lt;/em&gt; for online shopping, and so on. Then using inbox rules, all e-mails are automatically sorted into folders as soon as they reach my inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only am I dealing with less e-mail overall since switching services forced me to unsubscribe from all the junk I signed up for over the years, I'm also spending my time more efficiently when I have to go through my e-mails for the day. After using this system for more than 3 years, I'm very satisfied with how it continues to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Tutanota isn't your flavor, Protonmail is another popular choice for good reason. There's also a list of &lt;a href="https://prxbx.com/email/"&gt;privacy focused e-mail providers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Infosec"></category><category term="infosec"></category><category term="technology"></category></entry><entry><title>'Escaping e-mail hell: Revisited'</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/escaping-email-hell-revisited.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-11-05T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:johntrinh.net,2017-11-05:/escaping-email-hell-revisited.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;How to make your e-mail process more efficient&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;The problem with e-mail&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people spend a significant chunk of their working hours answering e-mails. With most people working remotely now, effective written communication is more important than ever. E-mail is part of the essential trifecta of systems that organize my life, along with my calendar and note-taking systems. The problem with e-mail, however, is that we spend too much time writing &amp;amp; organizing them without getting much value out of the time spent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inspiration for this story comes from Julie Zhuo’s &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-year-of-the-looking-glass/escaping-e-mail-hell-f55905f3862f"&gt;“Escaping e-mail hell”.&lt;/a&gt; I highly recommend her essay series &lt;em&gt;The Year of the Looking Glass&lt;/em&gt; as well as her book &lt;em&gt;The Making of a Manager&lt;/em&gt; for anyone who desires to improve their relationships, productivity, and well-being in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;How to write e-mails quickly &amp;amp; effectively&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, here's a summary of key points from Julie's article which addresses the question, &lt;em&gt;“How can I write more effective e-mails in less time?”&lt;/em&gt; I recommend reading the original for specific examples. Julie’s key points are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure your problem isn’t that you’re getting distracted while trying to write e-mails.&lt;/strong&gt; Spending too much time writing and getting distracted while trying to focus are two separate problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing detailed and concise e-mails are a skill you need to practice.&lt;/strong&gt; Like any other learned skill, you need to invest time &amp;amp; effort into getting better at it. Make a conscious effort to reduce the fluff in your e-mails until they're laser focused — the time savings will naturally come out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid squishy words.&lt;/strong&gt; Words matter — phrases like “I feel”, “I’m not sure”, and “perhaps” don’t convey confidence or clarity to the recipients. &lt;a href="https://owl.purdue.edu/owl/general_writing/academic_writing/active_and_passive_voice/active_versus_passive_voice.html"&gt;Passive voice&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. assigning responsibility to an object rather than a person) is the plague of many e-mails and can cause the dialogue to not move towards a solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a purpose before even starting to write an e-mail.&lt;/strong&gt; Think about specific questions that you need answers to, key points you want to make, and what you want the outcome of your e-mail to be. Create a high-level outline as a draft e-mail, then check for errors. With enough practice, this outline will &lt;em&gt;become&lt;/em&gt; the e-mail you send, saving you unnecessary revisions of lengthy e-mails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Highlight &lt;em&gt;Action Items&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;peoples' names&lt;/em&gt; in bold.&lt;/strong&gt; Don’t forget: you’re not the only person getting bombarded by dozens of e-mails every day. Make it easy for all of your recipients to be able to pick out what you expect from them, and by when. Corollary: Never copy anyone that doesn’t need to be on that e-mail chain. If you’re not sure, send those persons a separate short e-mail asking if they are working on that issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Never forward an e-mail to someone without a TL;DR.&lt;/strong&gt; Forwarding a long e-mail chain to someone with nothing in the body except &lt;em&gt;“Thoughts?”&lt;/em&gt; is like leaving a flaming bag of dog poop on their doorstep and running away. Using all the techniques above, summarize the key points &amp;amp; questions and what you need from them to go along with the forwarded e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;In practice&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After putting Julie’s sage advice into practice for more than five years now, I can attest to hours of time saved by avoiding needlessly long, unclear e-mails that required multiple revisions before hitting ‘Send’, not to mention the project hours saved from having to clarify badly written e-mails. My clients were happier, and they appreciated that I communicated with them clearly throughout the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julie's advice is great for writing better e-mails, but there was still the problem of organization. I found that using folders wasn't getting me much time savings, so as I explain in my process, the trick is to not really organize them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Good E-mail Inbox" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/good-email-inbox.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Stop using folders to organize e-mails&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to painstakingly sort all of my e-mails into separate folders by job number, but over time the number of folders grew too many, and I had to start throwing groups of folders into even more folders, organized by year or client. I realized that this was unsustainable, and I would frequently resort to using my e-mail client’s search function to look for a specific e-mail anyway. It took me more time to sort everything into folders than the time I got back in the few instances they even helped me find anything — a massive waste of time and energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One day I became frustrated with how my inbox looked and how long it took to find thing I'd archived months ago, and I scrapped all of my folders except for two:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Action Items&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sent Requests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;That's it!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few changes you need to make to your e-mail process in order to make this two-folder-only approach work. They boil down to some simple habits when dealing with each e-mail, and a change in philosophy. That philosophy is simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Keep your inbox as empty as possible.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds intimidating, but I promise it’s worth the effort and makes things much easier once you're set up. There’s nothing better than having a clean and uncluttered inbox at the end of the day, organized and ready to go for the next day. You’ll hopefully never again have to give someone the poor excuse of &lt;em&gt;“Sorry, I didn’t have time read your e-mail yet...”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Empty Inbox Checklist:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this work, you'll need to start relying on your e-mail client's search tool to find older e-mails. Make sure that whatever client you're using has a robust search &amp;amp; filtering tool. To make this easier, do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you send e-mails, always include the project number and a short description in the subject.&lt;/strong&gt; Similarly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you receive an e-mail, put a searchable text string (project number, name, and maybe a couple of keywords) at the bottom of your reply.&lt;/strong&gt; This way, you can always find it later using search even when you didn’t write the subject line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When your message includes an action item, a request, or a question for someone, make a copy of it in the ‘Sent Requests’ folder.&lt;/strong&gt; This makes it easy to pursue follow-ups and keep track of things that are stopping your work from moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Empty Inbox Process:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In recent years, I've learned that the most efficient way to handle e-mail is by scheduling time for it in my day to do them all at once (batching) instead of getting distracted by every notification. This isn't going to work for everyone, especially in fast-paced roles where immediate responses are critical. But the more you can batch your e-mails, the less you'll be distracted throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To streamline, check whether your e-mail client allows you to customize e-mail shortcuts, I use something like &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+A&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+R&lt;/code&gt; to move e-mails into the ‘Action Items’ and ‘Sent Requests’ folders will enable to you to fly through your inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the process I use when I sit down for 30 to 60 minutes to respond to everything in my inbox for the day. Don’t worry if you can’t get to all of them — prioritize the ones that are most important, and move the rest into the appropriate folder to act on later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Act on it now.&lt;/strong&gt; The idea is to get all of these little things done and onto someone else’s desk so you don't have to worry about it anymore (for now). These are usually short, simple tasks ranging from a quick reply to something I close out in 15 minutes. If it's a larger task or you can't do it now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move it to ‘Action Items’ and mark it as unread.&lt;/strong&gt; The number of unread messages in this folder acts as a quick count of unfinished tasks. I find that these are usually longer tasks that require a block of focused work of more than an hour. Once I have a good number of these, I work on them during my scheduled flow blocks (3-4 hours of uninterrupted distraction-free work time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delete stuff.&lt;/strong&gt; Don't be shy about deleting most of your e-mails. Most of them become useless after you've acted on them, and if it's actually important then it's likely documented somewhere else. The most common e-mails I delete are old responses in the same subject line. Most e-mail clients have a Conversation View which groups them all together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Archive it.&lt;/strong&gt; Once you think an e-mail chain has been closed out, archive it for a full record of the conversations that took place. These can also be e-mails you get copied on as an FYI, but don’t have any specific action items assigned to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Productivity"></category><category term="productivity"></category><category term="systems"></category></entry><entry><title>Four Books Every Engineer Should Read</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/four-books-every-engineer-should-read.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:johntrinh.net,2015-02-20:/four-books-every-engineer-should-read.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short list of books for engineers, students, and history nerds.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://d.lib.ncsu.edu/collections/catalog/00073901"&gt;&lt;img src="./images/professor-snyder.jpg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The Unwritten Laws of Engineering" by W.J. King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally published in 1944 as a series of three articles in the Mechanical Engineering magazine, King realized that the engineers of the day abided by a set of unspoken tenets which had, up until that point, been passed on only through tribal knowledge; hence the "unwritten" laws. These tenets served as encouragement for the next generation of engineers to develop their careers into successful ones they can be proud of. A must-read for any engineering student and fledgling engineer, and insightful even for an experienced engineer who might have discovered some of this wisdom through experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revised version, which has been expanded to include contemporary notes, is widely available for purchase - or access the articles as originally published here or here for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/multimedia-gallery/2006-1768hjpg?id=1119"&gt;&lt;img src="./images/minuteman.jpg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Inventing Accuracy: A Historical Sociology of Nuclear Missile Guidance" by Donald MacKenzie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without delving into the math and physics of guided missile design, MacKenzie describes in great detail how incredible were the blackbox guidance systems of the American nuclear arsenal; essentially, how the missile knew where it was by knowing where it wasn't. The book traces the history of guided missile design through multiple wars, different governments, and numerous research labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, MacKenzie discusses ballistic missile development in a sociohistorical context: the internal and external pressures, how the scientific community battled with one another to reach a consensus on what design to use, and how the government initially rejected the need to develop a these guidance systems, but later demanded it when the idea became technologically feasible. There is a strong analogy to Kennedy's space race and the Apollo program here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/inventing-accuracy
http://www.jstor.org/stable/2781396&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img src="./images/SR-71-cockpit.jpeg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Sled Driver: Flying the World's Fastest Jet" by Brian Shul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, this book places the reader into the cockpit of the SR-71 Blackbird. Shul's stylistic writing along with his excellent photography combine to give one of aviation's best and most memorable books on training for and operating the SR-71 Blackbird. Unfortunately Sled Driver was limited to a production of only 3500 copies, but you can find scanned versions floating around on the net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shul goes into relatively minor engineering detail on the Blackbird, overviewing the challenges faced during development… but his main work is in describing the practical "as flown" experience of the jet, both at home and deep into enemy territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll also find the sequel, The Untouchables, written with his then co-pilot Walter Watson, a treat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img src="./images/Apollo-nav-computer.jpeg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The Soul of a New Machine" by Tracy Kidder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kidder takes us back to 1978, when the bipolar junction transistor (BJT) had been invented just seven years prior, and computers were being built with thousands of specialized integrated circuits and individual logic units. The story follows a group of young computer scientists and engineers who are tasked with creating the next 32-bit computer, and how they spent nights working overtime in the office basement for weeks and months at a time - not because they were getting paid to - but simply because they loved what they did. Kidder's telling of how this team of young guys overcame the tremendous challenges in developing the newest technology of that decade is unsurpassed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of those engineers exemplifies the pure passion, work ethic, and ingenuity that is so quintessential in describing the legendary engineers of America's heyday, from Neil Armstrong to Kelly Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reading List"></category><category term="engineering"></category><category term="books"></category></entry></feed>