<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Practical Systems Engineering - Infosec</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://johntrinh.net/feeds/infosec.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://johntrinh.net/</id><updated>2020-09-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering of the Mind</subtitle><entry><title>5 Apps to Improve Your Security &amp; Privacy in 2019 (Updated for 2020)</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/5-apps-to-improve-your-security-and-privacy-in-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-23T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:johntrinh.net,2019-06-23:/5-apps-to-improve-your-security-and-privacy-in-2019.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short list of apps to streamline your personal online security &amp;amp; privacy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t receive any compensation, monetary or otherwise, from the products, companies, or developers of the apps discussed in this article.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; There are many privacy-focused apps listed on &lt;a href="https://prism-break.org/en/"&gt;PRISM Break.&lt;/a&gt; If there's an app or function you're looking for outside the scope of this article, chances are there's something listed there you can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As online technologies continue to grow, data collection and surveillance on users has become the norm. The entities who do this are not only &lt;a href="https://www.eff.org/nsa-spying"&gt;government agencies,&lt;/a&gt; but also &lt;a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/08/when-it-comes-to-internet-privacy-be-very-afraid-analyst-suggests/"&gt;corporations&lt;/a&gt; and the very companies that develop the tools we all use. It’s no surprise given how lucrative data collection has become as a business model for internet companies like Google and Facebook to &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/2018/4/11/17177842/facebook-advertising-ads-explained-mark-zuckerberg"&gt;sell ads and share personal data with third-parties.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s disheartening for me to see the weekly headlines of millions of users’ worth of data being hacked, or that the companies we’ve entrusted our information with have decided to do questionable or unethical things with our data for profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="nulltext" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/kill-code.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even worse, our &lt;a href="https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2018/4/10/17222062/mark-zuckerberg-testimony-graham-facebook-regulations"&gt;government seems incapable of dealing with these issues,&lt;/a&gt; either because they lack the technical expertise, or perhaps because it simply isn’t a priority issue in our current political climate. It’s hard not to feel powerless, and yet all of us rely on these tools as a part of daily life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Opting out doesn’t work. It’s nonsense to tell people not to carry a credit card or not to have an email address. And “buyer beware” is putting too much onus on the individual. People don’t test their food for pathogens or their airlines for safety. The government does it. But the government has failed in protecting consumers from internet companies and social media giants. But this will come around. The only effective way to control big corporations is through big government. —&lt;a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/08/when-it-comes-to-internet-privacy-be-very-afraid-analyst-suggests/"&gt;Bruce Schneier, 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Several years ago, I decided to do something to protect my online privacy so that I’d have some protection when the real-world situation gets worse. My hope is that you’ll be convinced it’s not as difficult and time-consuming to do as you might imagine, and get motivated to protect yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These apps aren’t a magic bullet; they’re simply tools. The real benefits come from changing some of your bad online habits and adopting better ones. Even if you don’t adopt every aspect today, acknowledging that your online privacy isn’t good enough and committing to improve over time is a great first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;1. Iridium Browser, Brave, and Firefox&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Iridium" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/iridium-browser.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Google Chrome has taken over the internet. As of 2019, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usage_share_of_web_browsers"&gt;it’s used by more than 60% of all devices!&lt;/a&gt; And for good reasons: it’s one of the more secure, actively developed browsers for desktop and mobile devices, and it’s packed with convenient features. But in recent years, it’s been &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2019/06/21/google-chrome-has-become-surveillance-software-its-time-switch/"&gt;under scrutiny&lt;/a&gt; for adding questionable features that invade user privacy, and &lt;a href="https://blog.cryptographyengineering.com/2018/09/23/why-im-leaving-chrome/"&gt;keep them handcuffed to the Google ecosystem.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a challenge to find a desktop web browser that’s based on the open-source Chromium code like Google Chrome is, but without all of the baggage. I finally found an alternative in &lt;a href="http://iridiumbrowser.de/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iridium Browser,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is an open-source project that focuses on security and privacy. If you don’t have a strong preference for the Chromium look &amp;amp; feel, &lt;a href="https://www.mozilla.org/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firefox&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://brave.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brave&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are other great options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of which browser you decide to use, don’t forget to add the following extensions for maximum protection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uBlock Origin + uBlock Origin Extra &lt;em&gt;(Note: Adblock Plus is no longer trustworthy)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTTPS Everywhere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;2. Brave for mobile&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Brave" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/brave-browser.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for mobile browsers, I’m a big fan of &lt;a href="https://brave.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brave&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is available for iOS and Android. It comes with the best mobile ad-blocker I’ve ever used (it can even block YouTube ads and allow video playback in the background while your phone is locked). The experience feels extremely optimized and lightweight compared to any other mobile browser I’ve used in the past 7 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While they are a for-profit company, &lt;a href="https://www.computerworld.com/article/3292619/the-brave-browser-basics-what-it-does-how-it-differs-from-rivals.html"&gt;they’re trying to improve the way ads are used&lt;/a&gt; by only allowing ads with your consent, ads that don’t collect your data, and giving users more control over what types of ads they see. Oftentimes ads are the only way some of our favorite websites can continue to operate, so this respectful user-focused approach is refreshing to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;3. 1Password or Bitwarden&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="1Password" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/1password-preview.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Passwords are a necessary evil for most services connected to the internet. The best way to create a truly secure (hard to crack) password is by making it longer, on the order of 32+ characters — but this is at odds with human nature since we want to use passwords that are easy to remember and type out. In other words, we’re lazy and our passwords suck. &lt;a href="https://haveibeenpwned.com/"&gt;It’s possible that some of your passwords have already been leaked.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve also met many people who store their passwords in a Word/text file on their computer, or wrote them all down on a legal pad. Not only is this insecure, but if you ever lost it in a hard drive failure, fire, theft, or hack, it’s game over — you’d never fully recover. Simplistic systems like this aren’t going to cut it if you want to protect yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Password managers are the solution. The idea is to create one &lt;a href="https://www.schneier.com/essays/archives/2014/02/choosing_a_secure_pa.html"&gt;secure and memorable passphrase&lt;/a&gt; that you commit to memory forever, and use that to login to a service or app that manages the rest of your passwords for you. The manager should also help you generate secure/randomized passwords since you no longer have to remember them for each individual account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2019, my most recommended services are &lt;a href="https://1password.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1Password&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, followed by &lt;a href="https://bitwarden.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bitwarden.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I researched these based on security, ease of use, and integration with browser &amp;amp; mobile. I also encourage you to check out &lt;a href="https://www.lastpass.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LastPass&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.dashlane.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dashlane&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to see which one you like best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before using any password manager, make sure you trust that your desktop and phone aren’t compromised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;4. Authy&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Authy" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/authy-preview.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two-factor authentication (2FA), also known as One-Time Passwords (OTP), is an effective way to secure an account by separating the login credentials into two parts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something you know,&lt;/strong&gt; i.e. your username &amp;amp; passphrase&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Something you have,&lt;/strong&gt; i.e. your phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you log in to an account with 2FA enabled, the website will ask you for an additional code that’s randomly generated and sent to your phone. All codes automatically expire every minute, ensuring that no one except you can use it. Some implementations of 2FA use e-mail and SMS text messages, but these aren’t fully secure because both message forms can be easily intercepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where &lt;a href="https://authy.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; comes in. If you decide to start using a password manager, the only things you should ever have to type in again are your master passphrase so you can manage your online accounts, and your 2FA codes. This solution works really well when you do them together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This might take you a day or two to set up, but isn’t as cumbersome as it first sounds. It’s well worth the increased security and peace of mind. If you do only one thing from this entire article, this is it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;5. Tutanota&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tutanota" src="https://johntrinh.net/images/tutanota-preview.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the hardest things I had to get rid of were my dozen or so e-mail addresses scattered across different services. I had several Gmail addresses, two with Outlook/Microsoft, Yahoo, and numerous others that I hardly ever used. Like many, I used Gmail as my primary e-mail service, and was fairly happy using it with their &lt;a href="https://support.google.com/mail/answer/15049?hl=en"&gt;HTML-only option.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t make the mistake of thinking you’re Facebook’s customer, you’re not — you’re the product. Its customers are the advertisers. —&lt;a href="https://www.information-age.com/facebook-is-deliberately-killing-privacy-says-schneier-1290603/"&gt;Bruce Schneier, 2010&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was prompted to switch away from Gmail last year when the &lt;em&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/em&gt; revealed that &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/7/2/17527972/gmail-app-developers-full-email-access"&gt;Google had been allowing third-party apps read data from your e-mails.&lt;/a&gt; Also don’t forget that &lt;a href="http://news.trust.org/item/20161004170601-99f8c"&gt;Yahoo was caught scanning e-mails for the NSA&lt;/a&gt; in 2016. I was upset, and disappointed in myself for not switching sooner. So began my search for an e-mail provider that wouldn’t violate my privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a lot of research, I decided on &lt;a href="https://www.tutanota.com/"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tutanota,&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which is available via web, iOS, and Android, and also has a dedicated desktop client for all platforms. Tutanota also comes with an encrypted calendar, which went live on July 8th, and has more features planned for development. While not as robust as Google Calendar&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a privacy-focused company, their code is open-source with development to allow outside auditing. They’re a company based in Germany, which means they’re GDPR-compliant and subject to Germany’s &lt;a href="https://www.dotmagazine.online/issues/security/germany-land-of-data-protection-and-security-but-why"&gt;strong privacy laws for individuals.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While you can use the limited Basic service for free, I pay $10/year for their Premium level, which gives me five different e-mail aliases, which are simply different addresses that all deliver e-mail to me. I selectively changed all of my online accounts to use a different alias depending on what the account is for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;em&gt;Address A&lt;/em&gt; for banking/finance; &lt;em&gt;Address B&lt;/em&gt; for social media; &lt;em&gt;Address C&lt;/em&gt; for online shopping, and so on. Then using inbox rules, all e-mails are automatically sorted into folders as soon as they reach my inbox.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only am I dealing with less e-mail overall since switching services forced me to unsubscribe from all the junk I signed up for over the years, I'm also spending my time more efficiently when I have to go through my e-mails for the day. After using this system for more than 3 years, I'm very satisfied with how it continues to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Tutanota isn't your flavor, Protonmail is another popular choice for good reason. There's also a list of &lt;a href="https://prxbx.com/email/"&gt;privacy focused e-mail providers.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Infosec"></category><category term="infosec"></category><category term="technology"></category></entry></feed>