<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Practical Systems Engineering - Reading List</title><link href="httpsL//johntrinh.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="httpsL/johntrinh.net/feeds/reading-list.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>httpsL//johntrinh.net/</id><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering of the Mind</subtitle><entry><title>Four Books Every Engineer Should Read</title><link href="httpsL/johntrinh.net/four-books-every-engineer-should-read.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:None,2015-02-20:httpsL/johntrinh.net/four-books-every-engineer-should-read.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short list of books for engineers, students, and history nerds.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://d.lib.ncsu.edu/collections/catalog/00073901"&gt;&lt;img src="./images/professor-snyder.jpg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The Unwritten Laws of Engineering" by W.J. King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally published in 1944 as a series of three articles in the Mechanical Engineering magazine, King realized that the engineers of the day abided by a set of unspoken tenets which had, up until that point, been passed on only through tribal knowledge; hence the "unwritten" laws. These tenets served as encouragement for the next generation of engineers to develop their careers into successful ones they can be proud of. A must-read for any engineering student and fledgling engineer, and insightful even for an experienced engineer who might have discovered some of this wisdom through experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revised version, which has been expanded to include contemporary notes, is widely available for purchase - or access the articles as originally published here or here for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/multimedia-gallery/2006-1768hjpg?id=1119"&gt;&lt;img src="./images/minuteman.jpg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Inventing Accuracy: A Historical Sociology of Nuclear Missile Guidance" by Donald MacKenzie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without delving into the math and physics of guided missile design, MacKenzie describes in great detail how incredible were the blackbox guidance systems of the American nuclear arsenal; essentially, how the missile knew where it was by knowing where it wasn't. The book traces the history of guided missile design through multiple wars, different governments, and numerous research labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, MacKenzie discusses ballistic missile development in a sociohistorical context: the internal and external pressures, how the scientific community battled with one another to reach a consensus on what design to use, and how the government initially rejected the need to develop a these guidance systems, but later demanded it when the idea became technologically feasible. There is a strong analogy to Kennedy's space race and the Apollo program here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/inventing-accuracy
http://www.jstor.org/stable/2781396&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img src="./images/SR-71-cockpit.jpeg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Sled Driver: Flying the World's Fastest Jet" by Brian Shul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, this book places the reader into the cockpit of the SR-71 Blackbird. Shul's stylistic writing along with his excellent photography combine to give one of aviation's best and most memorable books on training for and operating the SR-71 Blackbird. Unfortunately Sled Driver was limited to a production of only 3500 copies, but you can find scanned versions floating around on the net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shul goes into relatively minor engineering detail on the Blackbird, overviewing the challenges faced during development… but his main work is in describing the practical "as flown" experience of the jet, both at home and deep into enemy territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll also find the sequel, The Untouchables, written with his then co-pilot Walter Watson, a treat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img src="./images/Apollo-nav-computer.jpeg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The Soul of a New Machine" by Tracy Kidder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kidder takes us back to 1978, when the bipolar junction transistor (BJT) had been invented just seven years prior, and computers were being built with thousands of specialized integrated circuits and individual logic units. The story follows a group of young computer scientists and engineers who are tasked with creating the next 32-bit computer, and how they spent nights working overtime in the office basement for weeks and months at a time - not because they were getting paid to - but simply because they loved what they did. Kidder's telling of how this team of young guys overcame the tremendous challenges in developing the newest technology of that decade is unsurpassed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of those engineers exemplifies the pure passion, work ethic, and ingenuity that is so quintessential in describing the legendary engineers of America's heyday, from Neil Armstrong to Kelly Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reading List"></category><category term="engineering"></category><category term="books"></category></entry></feed>