<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Practical Systems Engineering - Reading List</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://johntrinh.net/feeds/reading-list.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://johntrinh.net/</id><updated>2021-11-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated><subtitle>Engineering of the Mind</subtitle><entry><title>Book Review: How to Win Friends and Influence People by Dale Carnegie</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/book-review-how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-07-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-11-28T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:johntrinh.net,2021-07-04:/book-review-how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Book review and field reference for "How to Win Friends and Influence People" by Dale Carnegie&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book probably needs no introduction. With tens of millions of copies sold far and wide since its first publication in 1936 and translations into over a dozen languages, it is consistently recommended by leaders in business, marketing, and management as required reading as a primer in human relations and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first picked up a copy in 2015 at Powell's City of Books in Portland, Oregon. While there were newer versions in paperback, I decided on an older 1981 revised version in hardback because I find there's a certain charm to old books. I only made it halfway through the book before I lost interest. I finally completed it a few weeks ago, and was inspired to write something about it. So what changed that got me to pick it back up and finish it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of my life, I didn't place a lot of value in relationships or social interaction. I grew up in a poor household, and learned at a young age how to "operate solo" -- to avoid relying on others for anything, because I needed to be able to take care of myself in difficult circumstances. I carried this mentality with me into my adult years, and in many ways negatively affected the way I formed relationships.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On top of that, being an introvert meant that socializing drains my energy, so I only made time for a few relationships that seemed meaningful. It took a lot of personal growth for me to develop my social skills, learn the nuances of healthy relationships, and to understand that it's okay to have relationships that only extend into certain areas of my life (e.g. networking for professional growth).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Professionally, I was the type who preferred to work quietly at my desk. It wasn't until years later that I learned one of the core tenets of successful engineering: effective communication and coordinated teamwork. Through my professional experiences over the past 9 years, I've come to understand importance, value, and power of building authentic relationships with other people, whether they are family or co-workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also read a few important books during the intervening years that enhanced my understanding of Carnegie's book. I hope to write reviews for them in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Thinking, Fast and Slow" by Daniel Kahneman, a keystone work in the field of psychology and behavioral economics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Daring Greatly" and other works by Brené Brown, an important body of work in modern everyday psychology on what it means to build compassion, empathy, and vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The Making of a Manager" by Julie Zhuo, which continues to be one of the most influential books I've read in recent years. I was also greatly inspired by her blog, &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-year-of-the-looking-glass"&gt;The Year of the Looking Glass.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Never Split the Difference" by Chris Voss: A field guide to effective negotiation tactics&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How This Review is Structured&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was difficult for me to write this review because of how much I wanted to cover, so I decided to split it into two sections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A relatively short review of the book itself, with my recommendation of whether or not it's useful in 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A field reference to the book with some of my personal notes added as a summary of each principle explained in the book. Since the book recommends that its readers review the concepts in the book every month to keep the concepts fresh, I think this would be useful for myself and others to use as a quick refresher. This section ended up being much longer than I anticipated, so I plan to update the notes over time as I gain more experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Section 1: Book Review&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've read a few self-help books, and some of them trace their inspiration to "How to Win Friends and Influence People", which made me excited to finally read it and understand what many consider to be the origin of the self-help movement. This book absolutely is as foundational as it's promoted to be, in the sense that the principles can be applied by anyone to achieve practical results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big caveat is that readers will have a hard time understanding &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; these tactics are effective without a good understanding of social psychology and other research on human behavior. This follows &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polanyi%27s_paradox"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polanyi's Paradox of Tacit Knowledge:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; "We know more than we can say" — we can learn how to drive a car without being able to explain exactly how a car works under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polanyi's paradox explains our ability to employ these tactics by relying on the accumulation of experiences rather than understanding textbook theories of why they work. In the case of this book, however, I believe it's important to have some understanding of the theories to counter one of the commonly leveled criticisms of this book, which is that it turns people into shallow salesmen. I don't believe that criticism is true, because like anything else, the book is a tool and the outcome depends only on how the tool is used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The books I mentioned earlier in this article are some of those theories, though they are just as practical as "How to Win Friends". By understanding compassion, empathy, and vulnerability, this can enable you to apply the principles taught by "How to Win Friends" in a more nuanced way for the different kinds of relationships in your life. Generally speaking, people want to build authentic &amp;amp; healthy relationships with the people in their family; not become a fake-nice pseudo salesman that avoids conflict for the sake of maintaining a distant, shallow relationship. On the other hand, people don't necessarily want to build deep friendships with all of their work colleagues, so putting on a veneer of friendliness can serve both parties by implying that the interaction is strictly professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is "How to Win Friends" still useful for people to read in 2022? I would say yes. But I would also point out that as a society, we've learned a lot of things about human behavior and social interaction since 1936 that I think is practically mandatory to study as a supplement to the principles in this book. Society has also been transformed completely by technology and the internet since the book was released. While this doesn't make the knowledge obsolete (far from it, in fact) it must be adapted in some ways, and I caution that it may not translate well through new forms of communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Section 2: Field Reference&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part of the review is a summary and quick reference guide to the principles of the book, along with some notes to illustrate each principle. The purpose is to create a useful guide for occasional review of these concepts as suggested by Carnegie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;In order to get the most out of this book:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a deep, driving desire to master the principles of human relations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read each chapter twice before going on to the next one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As you read, stop frequently to ask yourself how you can apply each suggestion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Underscore each important idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review this book each month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply these principles at every opportunity. Use this volume as a working handbook to help you solve your daily problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make a lively game out of your learning by offering some friend a dime or a dollar every time he or she catches you violating one of these principles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check up each week on the progress you are making. Ask yourself what mistakes you have made, what improvement, what lessons you have learned for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Keep notes in the back of this book showing how and when you have applied these principles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part One: Fundamental Techniques in Handling People&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section deals with the core principles of interacting with people. They are maxims that apply to nearly every situation, so you can think of them as the "Golden Rules" of this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.1) Don't criticize, condemn, or complain.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aim to understand the person and the situation they're in rather than criticizing them, offering advice right off the bat, or assuming they're acting irrationally. The best way to approach this is to listen and ask clarifying questions without making the other person feel like they're being judged. This technique is called "motivational interviewing," which is most often used to help people with healthy behavior change. Eventually you may reach a point where you can offer helpful and practical advice, where you can ask for permission to share your perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complaints that may seem small or innocuous could be perceived as an attack by others. Julie suggests that while in any business setting, you should filter everything you say as if everyone in the company will hear it eventually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2) Give honest and sincere appreciation.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, "Honest and sincere" means to be authentic. Authenticity happens when you speak straight from the heart without feeling like you need to filter what you say out of embarassment or judgement. This seems more applicable to personal relationship rather than business ones, where a certain amount of tact is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big theme in Brene Brown's work is to cultivate compassion towards others, even if your instinct is to disagree with them or their ideas. While it isn't easy, I've found that having this attitude of compassion and empathy makes it much easier for me to be authentic, even with complete strangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.3) Arouse in the other person an eager want.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"If out of reading this book you get just one thing -- an increased tendency to think always in terms of other people's point of view, and see things from their angle -- if you get that one thing out of this book, it may easily prove to be one of the building blocks of your career."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to think of this in another way: What does the other person value? Not only in terms of money or other material gain, but in terms of what &lt;strong&gt;personal values&lt;/strong&gt; they are trying to live up to. While there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; people who ruthlessly value money above all else, most professionals I know hold a variety of values; from the company vision to make the world better through the company's products, to something as straightforward as doing their job well to maintain the project budget, schedule, and risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By putting ourselves in someone else's shoes and understanding their core values, we can start to understand what motivates them to act. From this perspective, we can apply our creative problem-solving skills to come up with solutions that can allow both parties to come to a mutual agreement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part Two: Six Ways to Make People Like You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.1) Become genuinely interested in other people.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we may lead busy lives, we can (and should) certainly spare some time to get to know our friends, colleagues, and peers. Genuine interest should go beyond basic small talk about their work, interests, hobbies, romantic partner, and child(ren):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are does this person value?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is their personal and professional history? How did they get to where they are today?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do they spend their time outside of work? What are they passionate about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall and apply 'authenticity' from 1.2 and 'personal values' from 1.3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2) Smile.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smile sets up conversations for success. It can make us tend towards a friendly demeanor, and it can make other people feel at ease in a conversation. Body language is important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try your best not to fake a smile. Some people are highly empathetic and can detect subtle changes in body language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3) Remember that a person's name is to that person the sweetest and most important sound in any language.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do your best to remember another person's name. It's a small world even in the biggest cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I meet a new person, I add their name to my phone's to-do list with a small note about how, when, and where I met them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4) Be a good listener. Encourage others to talk about themselves.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The art of conversation seems to be lost on many of us who grew up in the Internet Age. So, how to have a conversation? Start by listening. You cannot apply the principle of becoming genuinely interested in other people (2.1) nor can you truly understand someone without &lt;strong&gt;intentional&lt;/strong&gt; listening. We often fall prey to our instinct to prove a point or to win a debate, but we know from psychological research that this often backfires and causes people to dig in on their beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practical Tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask questions with the purpose of understanding what the other person is trying to communicate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ask for permission to share, e.g. "Is it alright if I share my experience with you on this topic?"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2:1 question to sharing ratio when talking (i.e. not listening)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.5) Talk in terms of the other person's interests.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.6) Make the other person feel important -- and do it sincerely.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part Three: How to Win People to Your Way of Thinking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.1) The only way to get the best of an argument is to avoid it.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.2) Show respect for the other person's opinions. Never say, "You're wrong."&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.3) If you are wrong, admit it quickly and emphatically.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.4) Begin in a friendly way.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.5) Get the other person saying "yes, yes" immediately.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.6) Let the other person do a great deal of the talking.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.7) Let the other person feel that the idea is [theirs].&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.8) Try honestly to see things from the other person's point of view.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.9) Be sympathetic with the other person's ideas and desires.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.10) Appeal to the nobler motives.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.11) Dramatize your ideas.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3.12) Throw down a challenge.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Part Four: Be a Leader&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.1) Begin with praise and honest appreciation.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.2) Call attention to people's mistakes indirectly.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.3) Talk about your own mistakes before criticizing the other person.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.4) Ask questions instead of giving direct orders.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.5) Let the other person save face.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.6) Praise the slightest improvement and praise every improvement.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Corollary: Be "hearty in your approbation and lavish in your praise."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.7) Give the other person a fine reputation to live up to.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;4.8) Use encouragement. Make the fault seem easy to correct.&lt;/h3&gt;</content><category term="Reading List"></category><category term="reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Four Books Every Engineer Should Read</title><link href="https://johntrinh.net/four-books-every-engineer-should-read.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-07-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>John Trinh</name></author><id>tag:johntrinh.net,2015-02-20:/four-books-every-engineer-should-read.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short list of books for engineers, students, and history nerds.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://d.lib.ncsu.edu/collections/catalog/00073901"&gt;&lt;img src="./images/professor-snyder.jpg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The Unwritten Laws of Engineering" by W.J. King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally published in 1944 as a series of three articles in the Mechanical Engineering magazine, King realized that the engineers of the day abided by a set of unspoken tenets which had, up until that point, been passed on only through tribal knowledge; hence the "unwritten" laws. These tenets served as encouragement for the next generation of engineers to develop their careers into successful ones they can be proud of. A must-read for any engineering student and fledgling engineer, and insightful even for an experienced engineer who might have discovered some of this wisdom through experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revised version, which has been expanded to include contemporary notes, is widely available for purchase - or access the articles as originally published here or here for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://airandspace.si.edu/multimedia-gallery/2006-1768hjpg?id=1119"&gt;&lt;img src="./images/minuteman.jpg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Inventing Accuracy: A Historical Sociology of Nuclear Missile Guidance" by Donald MacKenzie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without delving into the math and physics of guided missile design, MacKenzie describes in great detail how incredible were the blackbox guidance systems of the American nuclear arsenal; essentially, how the missile knew where it was by knowing where it wasn't. The book traces the history of guided missile design through multiple wars, different governments, and numerous research labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, MacKenzie discusses ballistic missile development in a sociohistorical context: the internal and external pressures, how the scientific community battled with one another to reach a consensus on what design to use, and how the government initially rejected the need to develop a these guidance systems, but later demanded it when the idea became technologically feasible. There is a strong analogy to Kennedy's space race and the Apollo program here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sources:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/inventing-accuracy
http://www.jstor.org/stable/2781396&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img src="./images/SR-71-cockpit.jpeg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"Sled Driver: Flying the World's Fastest Jet" by Brian Shul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, this book places the reader into the cockpit of the SR-71 Blackbird. Shul's stylistic writing along with his excellent photography combine to give one of aviation's best and most memorable books on training for and operating the SR-71 Blackbird. Unfortunately Sled Driver was limited to a production of only 3500 copies, but you can find scanned versions floating around on the net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shul goes into relatively minor engineering detail on the Blackbird, overviewing the challenges faced during development… but his main work is in describing the practical "as flown" experience of the jet, both at home and deep into enemy territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll also find the sequel, The Untouchables, written with his then co-pilot Walter Watson, a treat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;img src="./images/Apollo-nav-computer.jpeg" width="500"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;"The Soul of a New Machine" by Tracy Kidder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kidder takes us back to 1978, when the bipolar junction transistor (BJT) had been invented just seven years prior, and computers were being built with thousands of specialized integrated circuits and individual logic units. The story follows a group of young computer scientists and engineers who are tasked with creating the next 32-bit computer, and how they spent nights working overtime in the office basement for weeks and months at a time - not because they were getting paid to - but simply because they loved what they did. Kidder's telling of how this team of young guys overcame the tremendous challenges in developing the newest technology of that decade is unsurpassed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The journey of those engineers exemplifies the pure passion, work ethic, and ingenuity that is so quintessential in describing the legendary engineers of America's heyday, from Neil Armstrong to Kelly Johnson.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reading List"></category><category term="engineering"></category><category term="books"></category></entry></feed>